Finding Aid for George Romney Papers 1920s-1973
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Governor's Papers
  - Political/Miscellaneous
    - Political Files
      - 1962
        - Romney gubernatorial campaign (Box 353)
          - Subject file
            - Veterans (Box 356)
            - Volunteers, 3 folders (Box 356)
            - War Record (Box 356)
            - Women for Romney (Box 356)
            - Young Republican Clubs (Box 356)
          - Campaign notebook, 1 folders (Box 356)
          - Campaign miscellanea (in box 439) (Box 356)
        - Transition Office and Inauguration
          - Pre-Inaugural Meetings (Box 356)
          - Inauguration (Box 356)
          - Acceptances (December) (Box 356)
          - Pre-Inauguration Correspondence (Box 356)
      - 1963
        - Correspondence and RSCC releases (Box 356)
      - 1964
        - Republican National Convention
          - Speeches, press releases, etc., 5 folders (Box 357)
          - Convention Schedules, 2 volumes (Box 357)
        - Republican National Committee (Box 357)
        - Republican State Convention May 1964 (Box 357)
        - Romney gubernatorial campaign
          - Advance File
            - Advance Manual (Box 357)
            - Advance Men (Box 357)
            - Advance Reports (Box 357)
            - Advance Schedule (Box 357)
            - Blitz, 2 folders (Box 357)
            - Campaign Information (Box 357)
            - Candidate's Wives Tour (Box 357)
            - Contacts (Box 357)
            - County Conventions (Box 357)
            - District Organization Reports (Box 357)
            - GOP Girl Chairmen (Box 357)
            - Media Commercials (Box 357)
            - Romney Wagon Schedule (Box 357)
            - Wayne County, 2 folders (Box 357)
          - Schedule Files (arranged by week) (Box 357)
          - Schedule Files (arranged by week) (Box 358)
          - Subject File
            - Advance Reports (Box 358)
            - Advertising (Box 358)
            - Budget (Box 358)
            - Campaign Chairmen (correspondence and planning) (Box 358)
            - Campaign Contributions, 2 folders (Box 358)
            - Campaign Organization (Box 359)
            - Campaign - Republican Leaders (Box 359)
            - Campaign Strategy (Box 359)
            - Contacts (Box 359)
            - Economic Club Debate (Box 359)
            - Ethnic Groups (Box 359)
            - Little (Peg) file (Box 359)
            - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 359)
            - Nationalities Division (Box 359)
            - Petitions (Box 359)
            - Petition Circulators (Box 359)
            - Platform (Box 359)
            - Platform Committee (Box 359)
            - Polls (Box 359)
            - Press Summary (Box 359)
            - Research (Box 359)
            - Special Groups (Box 359)
            - Staff Meetings (Box 359)
            - Staff Memoranda and Correspondence (Box 359)
        - Miscellaneous
          - Republican State Central Committee (Box 359)
          - Record of Progress (1964) (Box 359)
          - Notebook: Campaign Schedule by City (Box 359)
          - Notebook: Campaign Organization and Staff (Box 359)
          - Michigan "Swing Candidates": Gary Brown, Marvin Esch, Jack MacDonald, Donald Riegle, Philip Ruppe and George Washington (Box 359)
          - Campaign Materials (Box 359)
      - 1965
        - Republican State Central Committee (Box 360)
        - Republican State Convention, September 10-12 (Box 360)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 360)
        - Inauguration
          - Press Releases (Box 360)
          - Romney, Lenore (Box 360)
          - Medallions (Box 360)
          - Committee Reports (Box 360)
          - Miscellaneous, 2 folders (Box 360)
      - 1966
        - Campaign Headquarters (Box 360)
        - Candidates (Box 360)
        - Convention (State) (Box 360)
        - Convention Platform (Box 360)
        - Republican Organization (Box 360)
        - Speeches (Box 360)
        - Subject File
          - Advance Men (Box 360)
          - Campaign Count-down (Box 360)
          - Congressional Statements (Box 360)
          - Correspondence (Box 360)
          - County Chairmen (Box 360)
          - County Coordinators (Box 360)
          - DC-3 Blitz (Box 360)
          - Executive Staff (Box 360)
          - Election Night (Box 360)
          - GOP Girls (Box 360)
          - GOP State Convention (Box 360)
          - Gubernatorial Race (Box 360)
          - Griffin (Senatorial) Race (Box 360)
          - Headquarters (Box 360)
          - Helicopter Blitz (Box 360)
          - Campaign Materials (Box 360)
          - Campaign Materials Requested (Box 360)
          - Michigan State Fair (Box 360)
          - Mrs. Lenore Romney (Box 360)
          - National Jaycees (Box 360)
          - Personnel Files (Box 360)
          - Precinct Delegates (Box 360)
          - Research (Box 361)
          - Telethon (General) (Box 361)
          - Telethons (notebook) (Box 361)
          - Telethons
            - Detroit (Box 361)
            - Flint (Box 361)
            - Jackson (Box 361)
            - Kalamazoo (Box 361)
            - Marquette (Box 361)
            - State-wide (Box 361)
            - Michigan Week (Box 361)
          - Television commercials (Box 361)
          - Women Out Working (WOW): Bank account, bills (Box 361)
          - Women Out Working show (Box 361)
          - Women Out Working campaign notebooks, 2 volumes (Box 361)
          - Election Night (Box 361)
          - Post-party Celebration (Box 361)
          - Romney Birthday Party July 1966 (Box 361)
          - Campaign materials, 3 folders (Box 361)
          - Neighborhood Headquarters: "Operation Grassroots" (Box 362)
          - Post-election evaluation (Box 362)
          - County Profile Book, 1 volumes (Box 362)
          - Michigan Congressional districts, 1 volumes (Box 362)
          - "Wayne County 'Who's Who'" (Box 362)
          - Final campaign report (Box 362)
          - Form letters (arranged by topic) (Box 362)
          - Scheduling (Box 362)
      - 1967
        - Miscellaneous (Box 362)
        - Convention (February) (Box 362)
        - Survey of county chairmen (Box 362)
      - 1968
        - State Convention (April) (Box 362)
        - State Convention (August) (Box 362)
        - National Convention (Box 362)
        - Republican Governors Association (communications with Ronald Reagan) (Box 362)
      - Fourteenth Congressional District Controversy 1962-1966
        - Clippings, correspondence, and memoranda (Box 363)
      - Name file
        - Correspondence, etc. with other public figures 1963-1968
          - Brooke, Edward (Box 363)
          - Eisenhower, Dwight, 2 folders (Box 363)
          - Goldwater, Barry, 3 folders (Box 363)
          - Nixon, Richard (Box 363)
          - Percy, Charles (Box 363)
          - Reagan, Ronald (Box 363)
          - Rockefeller, Nelson (Box 363)
          - Scranton, William (Box 363)
          - Seligman, Eustace (Box 363)
          - Summerfield, Arthur (Box 363)
          - Van Dusen, Richard (Box 363)
    - Miscellaneous
      Miscellaneous is comprised of smaller sets of files that were maintained separately by the governor's office. Here are files relating to Romney's appointments to state boards and commissions, extradition materials (1962-1963 only), formal appointment orders, agenda for the State Board of Education, minutes of the Michigan Employment Security Commission, and various printed material generated by a state board/commission or relating to a public issue (such as the new constitution or tax reform).
      - Miscellaneous personal/political/administrative
        - 1962-1968, 9 folders (Box 363)
        - Letters of congratulations upon accepting position as secretary of the Department of Housing and Urban Development December 1968 (Box 363)
        - Appointments file (GR's recommendations re: additional appointments in the Nixon administration), 2 folders (Box 363)
      - Appointments to Boards and Commissions 1963-1968
        - Name files (Box 379)
        - Name files (Box 380)
        - Name files (Box 381)
        - Name files (Box 382)
        - Name files (Box 383)
        - Name files (Box 384)
        - Name files (Box 385)
        - Name files (Box 386)
        - Name files (Box 387)
        - Name files (Box 388)
        - Name files (Box 389)
        - Name files (Box 390)
        - Name files (Box 391)
        - Name files (Box 392)
        - Name files (Box 393)
        - Name files (Box 394)
        - Name files (Box 395)
        - Name files (Box 396)
      - Extraditions 1962-1963
        - Case files (Box 397)
        - Case files (Box 398)
      - Orders for appointments
        - Appointment files (Box 399)
      - State Board of Education
        - Agenda 1966 (Box 400)
        - Agenda 1966 (and related) (Box 401)
        - Agenda 1967 (Box 402)
        - Agenda 1967 (Box 403)
        - Agenda 1967 (Box 404)
        - Agenda 1968 (Box 405)
        - Agenda 1968 (Box 406)
        - Agenda 1968 (Box 407)
      - Michigan Employment Security Commission
        - Minutes 1963-August 1965 (Box 407)
        - Minutes September 1965-January 1966 (Box 408)
      - Printed material (arranged by name of commission or board)
        - A-E (Box 408)
        - E-L (Box 409)
        - L-V (Box 410)
      - Printed material (arranged by topic)
        - Constitution (Box 411)
        - Olympic Committee (Box 411)
        - Taxation and fiscal reform (Box 411)
        - Detroit/Wayne County (Box 412)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 412)
        - Budget and capital outlay studies (Box 413)
      - Miscellaneous (not filed)
        - Notebook of appointments to boards and commissions (Box 414)
        - Papers re: Ecorse Public School System 1961-1964 (Box 414)
        - Papers re: anti-poverty program circa 1966-1967 (Box 414)
        - Papers re: American Motors and automotive industry (Box 414)
        - Books containing marginal notes (Box 414)
      - Miscellaneous (1983 accession)
        - State Capitol Building Restoration and/or Expansion proposals, correspondence, and planning materials 1966-1968 (Box 424)
        - Topical Files (1983 accession)
          - Agriculture, State Fair Authority 1967-1967 (Box 425)
          - Conservation (re: pesticides) (Box 425)
          - Crime Commission 1967-1969, 2 folders (Box 425)
          - Crime and Law Enforcement briefing material (Box 425)
          - Election of 1962: Press releases (Box 425)
          - Good Samaritan Law (Box 425)
          - Health Briefing 1968 (Box 425)
          - Interstate Oil Compact Commission 1968 (Box 425)
          - Kalamazoo odor problem 1968 (Box 425)
          - Midland Plant; Preliminary Safety Analysis Report, Vol. III (Box 425)
          - Migrant Labor 1967-1969 (Box 425)
          - Office of Economic Opportunity, Grant Log 1965-1967 (Box 425)
          - Partners of the Alliance, 2 folders (Box 426)
          - Romney Record 1966-1968 (Box 426)
          - Romney resignation (Box 426)
          - Social Services, Department of (Box 426)
          - Special Commissions (Box 426)
          - Traffic Safety (Box 426)
          - Transportation (Box 426)
          - Unemployment (Box 426)
          - Veterans (Box 426)
          - Vocational Education (Box 426)
          - Water Pollution (Box 426)
          - Youth (Box 426)
          - Youth for Understanding (Box 426)
- Pre-gubernatorial papers
  The Pre-Gubernatorial subgroup of the George Romney papers consists of material from the period of 1939-1962, and documents Romney's management of American Motors, his involvement with Citizens for Michigan, and his activities as delegate to Michigan's constitutional convention of 1961-1962. The subgroup concludes with materials from Romney's successful campaign for governor in 1962. The subgroup presently totals 21 linear feet (15 linear feet of files and 6 linear feet of sound recordings described as part of the Sound Recordings subgroup).
  In addition to George Romney's public career, the Pre-Gubernatorial subgroup also documents Romney's private activities. The subgroup includes an important file of both personal correspondence and correspondence pertaining to his activities and interests in the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-Day Saints (Mormon). Romney also maintained correspondence with members of his immediate family and other Romney relatives which has been included with this series.
  Of noteworthy interest, the Pre-Gubernatorial subgroup contains copies of the letter which Romney wrote to presidential candidates, John Kennedy and Richard Nixon, during the campaign of 1960. Romney outlined for the candidates some of the major issues facing the country. The subgroup includes the responses of the candidates to Romney's critique.
  As with the other subgroups within the George Romney papers, the Pre-Gubernatorial subgroup includes Romney's speech file for the period 1942-1962. There is also a large series of audio-tapes of most of these speeches. These are listed in the finding aid to the Sound Recordings subgroup.
  - Biographical information
    - Draft of Tom Mahoney's biography of GWR (Box 1-E)
      (with Romney's marginal note and corrections)
    - Biographical file (Box 1-E)
    - Articles and publicity about GR (Box 1-E)
  - Correspondence
    - Personal
      - 1939-1954, 11 folders (Box 1-E)
      - 1955-1962, 6 folders (Box 2-E)
        (no 1960)
    - Church
      - 1944-1957, 13 folders (Box 2-E)
        (no 1945)
      - 1958-1962, 5 folders (Box 3-E)
    - Family (immediate and relatives)
      - 1956-1962, 13 folders (Box 3-E)
  - Speeches/articles
    - 1941-July 1957 (Box 4-E)
    - September 1957-October 1958 (Box 5-E)
    - November 1958-March 1959 (Box 6-E)
    - April-October 1959 (Box 7-E)
    - November 1959-May 1960 (Box 8-E)
    - June 1960-January 1961 (Box 9-E)
    - February-September 1961 (Box 10-E)
    - October 1961-June 1962 (Box 11-E)
    - July-December 1962 (Box 12-E)
    - Speech background materials (Box 12-E)
    - Undated and unidentified speech cards (Box 12-E)
  - Business career
    - Nash-Kelvinator Corporation (Box 13-E)
    - American Motors (Box 13-E)
  - Public service
    - Citizens' Advisory Committee to Detroit Board of Education 1958 (Box 14-E)
    - Citizens for Michigan (Box 14-E)
    - Constitutional Convention (Box 14-E)
    - Election 1960 (includes open letter to candidates Nixon and Kennedy with their responses as well as the responses of others) (Box 15-E)
    - Gubernatorial campaign 1962
      (Campaign speeches filed in Speeches/articles series)
      - Press releases February-December 1962, 2 folders (Box 15-E)
      - Campaign issues (Box 15-E)
      - Issue statements (Box 15-E)
      - Personal/political correspondence October-December 1962 (Box 15-E)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Romney family (Box 15-E)
    - Gaskell Romney (Box 15-E)
    - Clippings (Box 15-E)
    - Various (Box 15-E)
- Post-Gubernatorial papers
  This subgroup of papers covers the period when Romney served in the Nixon administration as Secretary of Housing and Urban Development, 1969-1972. Included also are files documenting Secretary Romney's involvement with the voluntary action movement, first as chairman of the Cabinet Sub-Committee on Voluntary Action, later as executive board member of the National Center for Voluntary Action. A smaller portion of this series relates to the Concerned Citizens Movement, an organization established to educate people in public affairs and to serve as a citizens watchdog over various government activities.
  The subgroup has been arranged into six series: HUD Subject Files; Voluntary Action; Concerned Citizens Movement; Later Career; Personal Papers; and Speeches.
  - HUD Subject Files
    The HUD Subject File (13.5 linear feet; 1969-1973) consists of memoranda, reports, correspondence, clippings, and some published materials relating to Romney's service as Secretary of Housing and Urban Development. This series documents Romney's achievements in the area of housing: increased housing production during his administration, the development of new financial devices through the Governmental National Mortgage Association to make available and to secure mortgage monies, the "New Communities" program designed to provide thousands of new homes to thirteen new community developments, and "Operation Breakthrough," a program that sought to stimulate improvements in the housing industry. This series also provides information about Romney's role as administrator of an important cabinet position and of his relationship with President Nixon and members of the president's immediate staff. The researcher should realize that this series, although rich in substantive memoranda and correspondence, does not provide a complete picture of the operation of HUD during the 1969-1972 period; for that, the researcher is of course directed to the National Archives and to the archives maintained by HUD itself.
    - Advisory Committee (Box 1-P)
    - Advisory Committee on Intergovernmental Relations (ACIR), 10 folders (Box 1-P)
    - Applicants and candidates for HUD positions (Box 1-P)
    - Appropriations (Box 1-P)
    - Attorney General John Mitchell (Box 1-P)
    - Blue Collar Workers, Domestic Council Subcommittee on (Box 1-P)
    - Budget
      - 1969
        - General (Box 1-P)
        - Budget appeal 1969 (Box 1-P)
        - Fiscal year 1971 (Box 1-P)
    - Budget
      - 1970
        - General, 2 folders (Box 2-P)
      - 1971
        - General, 3 folders (Box 2-P)
      - 1972
        - General, 5 folders (Box 2-P)
    - Burns, Arthur (Box 2-P)
    - Cabinet meetings, 6 folders (Box 2-P)
    - Cabinet (memoranda, etc.) (Box 2-P)
    - Cabinet committees - General (Box 2-P)
    - Cabinet Committee on Construction, 1 folders (Box 2-P)
    - Cabinet Committee on Construction, 8 folders (Box 3-P)
    - Cabinet Committee on Economic Policy, 4 folders (Box 3-P)
    - Cabinet Committee on Education (Box 3-P)
    - Cabinet Committee on Opportunity for the Spanish Speaking (Box 3-P)
    - Cabinet Committee on School Desegregation (Box 3-P)
    - Cambodia (Box 3-P)
    - Cannon, Mark (potential appointees at HUD) (Box 3-P)
    - Chapin, John (Box 4-P)
    - Church and related materials (Box 4-P)
    - Civil rights (Box 4-P)
    - Civil service and related (Box 4-P)
    - Commerce Department (Maurice Stans) (Box 4-P)
    - Community Development Corporation and community development program and grants, 4 folders (Box 4-P)
    - Committee on Interest Rates and Dividends (Box 4-P)
    - Complaint or grievance procedure (Box 4-P)
    - Congressional liaison and activity relating to HUD, 5 folders (Box 4-P)
      (SEE ALSO Patman, Wright)
    - Construction Industry Collective Bargaining Commission, 8 folders (Box 5-P)
    - Cost of Living Council, 11 folders (Box 5-P)
    - Council for Urban Affairs (Box 5-P)
    - Council of Economic Advisors (Box 5-P)
    - Declassified HUD documents (Box 5-P)
    - Defense Department (and related) (Box 5-P)
    - Denver housing (Box 5-P)
    - Detroit housing, 4 folders (Box 5-P)
    - Detroit housing, 5 folders (Box 6-P)
    - Domestic Council, 7 folders; 1 volumes (Box 6-P)
      [SEE ALSO National Growth Policy]
    - Environmental Quality Council (Box 6-P)
    - Equal opportunity (Box 6-P)
    - Federal Comprehensive Planning Assistance (Box 6-P)
    - Federal Home Loan Bank Board (Box 7-P)
    - Federal Housing Authority interest rates (Box 7-P)
    - Federal National Mortgage Association, 5 folders (Box 7-P)
    - Field directors, meeting with October 1970 (Box 7-P)
    - Finger, Harold B. (Box 7-P)
    - Group interviews - HUD - December 1972 (Box 7-P)
    - Government National Mortgage Association (Box 7-P)
    - Gulledge, Eugene (Box 7-P)
    - Health, Education and Welfare, Department of (Elliott Richardson) (Box 7-P)
    - Housing abandonment (Box 7-P)
    - Housing Assistance Research Program (Box 7-P)
    - Housing costs - lumber (Box 7-P)
    - Housing Goals Report (Box 7-P)
    - Housing Production Targets (Box 7-P)
    - Housing programs (Box 7-P)
    - Housing statistics (Box 7-P)
    - HUD's future (Box 7-P)
    - HUD inheritance 1969 (Box 7-P)
    - Indian (native American) housing (Box 7-P)
    - Inner-city housing and FHA mortgage insurance (Box 7-P)
    - Inspector General and Government Accounting Office (Box 7-P)
    - Interagency Committee on Construction Costs (Box 8-P)
    - Interior Department (Rogers Morton) (Box 8-P)
    - International affairs, 2 folders (Box 8-P)
    - Judge, James J. (Box 8-P)
    - Kaiser-Douglas Commissions (Box 8-P)
    - Land Use and Development Sub-committee (Box 8-P)
    - Legal matters, 2 folders (Box 8-P)
    - Legislative proposals 1971 (Box 8-P)
    - McKinney, Harold (memoranda), 3 volumes; 1 folders (Box 8-P)
    - Management Issues meeting 1970 (Box 8-P)
    - Manpower Management Team (Box 8-P)
    - Mayors and cities (Box 8-P)
    - Memoranda, 6 folders (Box 8-P)
    - Metropolitan development (Box 9-P)
    - Minority entrepreneurship (Box 9-P)
    - Model Cities
      - General, 4 folders (Box 9-P)
      - Budget FY 1972 (Box 9-P)
      - New Towns Sub-Committee (Box 9-P)
    - Morgan, John H. (Box 9-P)
    - Mortgage and interest (Box 9-P)
    - Mortgage Bankers Association of America (Box 9-P)
    - Nader Associates (Ralph Nader) (Box 9-P)
    - National Advisory Committee on Low Cost Housing (Box 9-P)
    - National Association for Housing Partnerships (Box 9-P)
    - National Association of Home Builders (Box 9-P)
    - National Association of Housing and Redevelopment Officials (Box 9-P)
    - National Association of Real Estate Boards (Box 9-P)
    - National Council on Indian Opportunity (Box 10-P)
    - National Growth Policy Report, 5 folders (Box 10-P)
    - National Land Use Policy Act (Box 10-P)
    - National League of Cities (and U.S. Conference of Mayors) (Box 10-P)
    - National Urban Coalition (Box 10-P)
    - National Urban Development Bank (Box 10-P)
    - Neighborhood Development programs (Box 10-P)
    - New Communities, 2 folders (Box 10-P)
    - New Towns (Box 10-P)
    - Office of Economic Opportunity (and poverty) (Box 10-P)
    - Office of Management and Budget, 4 folders (Box 10-P)
    - Open Communities (Box 10-P)
    - Operating Committee (Box 10-P)
    - Patman, Wright (House Banking Committee) (Box 11-P)
    - Pennsylvania Avenue Commission (Box 11-P)
    - Political 1972 (Box 11-P)
    - Post Vietnam Study (Box 11-P)
    - Press and public relations (Box 11-P)
    - Property Disposition conference 1971 (Box 11-P)
    - Region V (Box 11-P)
    - Regional realignment (Box 11-P)
    - Revenue sharing (Box 11-P)
    - Romney, George
      - Awards and citations (Box 11-P)
      - Personal correspondence, 2 folders (Box 11-P)
      - Publicity and clippings, 5 folders (Box 11-P)
      - Resignation from HUD (Box 11-P)
    - Rules and regulations, publication of departmental (Box 11-P)
    - Rural Affairs Council (Box 11-P)
    - Rural development - Domestic Council (Box 11-P)
    - Rural housing (Box 11-P)
    - Section 236 (Box 11-P)
    - Solid Waste Subcommittee, Environmental Quality Council (Box 12-P)
    - Staff memoranda (Box 12-P)
    - Sprint (Box 12-P)
    - State Department (Box 12-P)
    - Sub-committees (Box 12-P)
    - Task Force on Urban Renewal (Box 12-P)
    - Telecommunication Policy (Clay T. Whitehead) (Box 12-P)
    - Television interviews (Box 12-P)
    - Tenant and site selection policies (Box 12-P)
    - TOP (The Option Process) (Box 12-P)
    - Transportation Department (John Volpe) (Box 12-P)
    - Treasury Department (David Kennedy) (Box 12-P)
    - Unger, Sherman (Box 12-P)
    - Urban Affairs Council, 4 folders (Box 12-P)
    - Urban Coalition (John Gardner) (Box 13-P)